do more productive efforts, specifically focused on third party's spend, which is upwards
of $10 billion for the company, and that is what we continue to do.
As we look at Q2, we actually see while gross margin, quarter-on-quarter gross margin has
been a negative, but SG&A as a percentage of sales has actually been a positive, negating
that gross margin impact.
And that, I would assume, I would think is, from a prognosis perspective, that is something
that we will continue towards the second half of the year.
Thank you.
Your next question comes from the line of James Quigley from Goldman Sachs.
Please go ahead.
Great.
Thank you for my questions.
I've got one on deals and M&As.
I think, Vaz, your quote on Bloomberg is you'd consider larger deals again.
So this is a bit of a transition into the commentary over the years.
A few years back, it was no big deals.
Then it was focused on bolt-ons.
Then we had avidity, which is large.
Later stage and a bit larger.
So what's changed, either internally at Novartis or externally, that's driven openness to larger
deals?
And what could a bigger deal look like in terms of strategic fit, given your therapeutic
areas and technology set?
Thank you.
Yeah, thanks, James.
I don't know what exactly Bloomberg wrote, but I can say there's no change in our M&A
strategy.
We've been, I think, disciplined and consistent that we focus on steady deals.
We've done a lot of small deals in the kind of sub-$2 billion range, which with the
upfronts in that range, often lower, and then selectively do larger deals in the range
of things like avidity when there is a compelling asset that fits with either our platform strategy
or our TA strategy or both, and avidity fit both.
So no change at all in our M&A strategy.
We don't need to do anything larger than that.
We have full confidence in our internal portfolio and pipeline and our R&D engine, and yet we
know we need to constantly supplement that engine with additional external innovation.
So you can expect just a continuation of what you've seen over the recent years.
Great.
Thank you.
Your next question comes from the line of Simon Baker from Roftal & Co.
Please go ahead.
Thank you for taking my question.